all right welcome to the solution
raising
on climate change i put out a call for
what topics were too big to tackle with
the solution raising
and a few people had mentioned this one
so i am excited to tackle it because i
don't
i spoiler alert i don't think anything's
too big for us to tackle the solution
crazy and i think there's always a way
to take an improvement forward so
solution raising is
a conversation in three parts we first
talk about what the world currently
looks like
we vent maybe even offer some some
things that are great that are happening
in that space
and then we switch over into our utopian
visions of the future what would it look
like
when everything solved in that area in
this case climate change we no longer
have to worry about it we tell our
grandkids we solved it and
they don't need to match one another's
so if someone else contradicts yours
it's perfectly fine because
spoiler alert we can actually create
utopias so then we move on to the
adjacent possible what we could actually
create together
that we would like to be part of that
involve
that only requires ten thousand people
and a hundred thousand dollars
and uh i was rewatching one of the old
solution raisings and i started the
first one
explaining that um the idea is to let
the conversation
emerge so though we do want to allow for
everyone to to talk we don't necessarily
need everyone to talk in every segment
so
you're encouraged to uh you know keep
your your thoughts precise
if you can i know i can't and and allow
it's like there's a sixth person here
which is the conversation right allowing
that to kind of
elaborate so who would like to start
sharing
with how they see solution raising i'm
sorry climate change
right now
well i'll kick off i mean i don't like
the word i don't like the term i think
it's i think it's
um misleading in a couple of ways i mean
firstly the climate is in a
constant state of change right and so
yeah climate change so what right
so it's change other than change that it
was supposed to be doing anyway
something like that right so i i don't
like the word on that level
the other thing i really don't like
about it is that it
has a tendency to focus the effort the
conversation the research the
media coverage etc entirely on carbon
dioxide
i much much much prefer the in term
environmental degradation or
environmental destruction or something
like
that so that we can you know in the same
conversation talk about plastic
and you know fertilizer runoff and
soil erosion and deforestation and all
of this kind of stuff right
um because it sort of leaves all of that
to the side right all of that can be
ignored because the big thing
is carbon dioxide so i'll just kick off
by saying that
i would just echo what eric said you
know i made a couple little notes coming
into here
that was the main one is and i've talked
to other friends about this
we need i think we need to be much more
concerned
about chemicals polluting
water systems landfill problems
more like chemical and general
waste yeah the temperature
i think will adapt and i don't think we
need to ignore
the earth's temperature i don't think
it's our main concern
and then other things on
one other topic that i see as a problem
is that it i don't think it's cool
to be
a person who is trying to be
environmentally sound
it's not cool and it's not sexy um
to do as little impact on the
environment as possible
the only way to be cool and be sexy and
get attention
is to be a consumer and show off the
stuff that you i have i
i don't understand
i mean even in even in finding a mate
like it's not cool to kind of do
nothing oh i'm cool because i do no
impact on
the environment i think we need
incentives
for people to be
low impact and i i don't see a world
like that
what are my incentives um
it's be nice to change that somehow
so i i definitely agree with the needing
incentives for
lower impact lifestyles i'm gonna play
devil's advocate a little bit on the
temperature problem being
a pressing problem and
mainly because of the concerns about
methane release in the arctic um
and us entering a feedback loop that we
can't control
so one of the focus focuses on
co2 reduction right now is uh to try to
prevent
uh melting of permafrost in the arctic
and release of
methane which has 27 times the
impact in terms of greenhouse gas
warming
of co2 um so
if we end up in that feedback loop we
may not be able to stop it
uh we may not be able to actually
control the temperature
and regulate the problem and we'd see
massive sea level rise we'd see droughts
uh large storms standard climate change
impacts magnified significantly so
i do think there is a place for having a
discussion about co2
and trying to control co2 emissions
um i don't really think i have too much
here to add that hasn't been said
already
um i'm trying to dig in and see if
there's anything that's
pressing um
i think my the
the the need that i
see is for a connected
ecosystem of data that can be made sense
of
to inform people
well that the
you know what to do um i i think that
that's
right now data's very disjointed there's
just a lot of
issues with reporting and and
how everything gets done and so um
to me it seems as if there needs to be
better practices in
making sense of what is going on
in the world via
you know technology um
you know i could add an example to that
i researched this but daniel i want to
just share mine
quickly uh just because i wanted to that
this one uh then
the topic was climate change and i did
think about what eric said like i also
i'm like there's such a bigger thing
by the environment and environmental
degradation all the crap we put into the
world not just co2
and the stuff that affects climate
climate and at the same time
the fact that it's a positive feedback
loop that like the more it rises the
more it's going to rise
um and we are a biological
human humans are biological and we can't
really deal with extreme temperatures
yet we're also really intelligent and so
we can adapt to extreme temperatures
and so there is we don't actually a
hundred percent know if humans are the
cause of climate change but we have to
deal with it either way
and so that was one of the reasons why i
put climate change at the topic was
but if it goes in the other direction
i'm fully okay with that but that
how do we if we're responsible
do something about it and if we're not
responsible
figure it out anyway because we've got
to figure out how to deal with this as
it comes and we're not going to be able
to do that under gaming
capitalism right like it's like well we
just need to create a for-profit model
to deal with the climate change
changes and so that's what i want daniel
if you wanted to add your
uh just real quickly for example i
always heard that
um that cows are adding to climate
change
um and it was something like they're
adding like
20 to 30 percent of the co2 emissions
and then i just recently heard that that
was wrong that it's only two percent
of the co2 emissions and it's not a big
deal and just goes back to jared's thing
on sense making
i i don't know what to believe now and
trying to understand
someone skewing the data where's this
coming from that
is so frustrating
yeah i mean i suspect it's some i mean i
don't know because i haven't seen these
data but i suspect it's something like
the two percent is talking about just
the cows right just the farting and the
and the breathing of the cows whereas
the 30 is talking about
all the land that's cleared in order to
make room for the cows and all the
transportation of the grain to the cows
and all of this kind of stuff is
included in the 30
words it's not included in the two
percent you know
so yeah no no no no but but it goes
exactly to your point about
confusion around the ability to make
sense because if there's no clear
understanding of what what these numbers
actually are representing then it's very
very very easy for them to be
misrepresentative you know exactly
exactly as you just pointed out
can i just pick up on something jared
said as well about this
this idea of a connected um
approach to delivering information and
being able to make choices because i
think that connected approach to
climate change is also really important
i mean this this thing about singling
out co2
unfortunately what it means is that the
whole um
financial economic industrial apparatus
orients itself around co2 reduction
right at any cost
right and the externalities involved in
that are way worse than the co2 was in
the first place you know so
this is this is the issue about about
focusing on co2 and so
you know there's i can't remember who
the guy was it's a really interesting
video
about soil that soil regeneration
alone if we were to return to a sort of
permaculture type
attitude towards global agriculture
that alone would solve the whole climate
thing right because the regeneration of
the soil microbiota
would absorb all the co2 necessary out
of the engine just like that right at
while at the same time regenerating the
soil so
connecting these things together and
understanding that soil erosion and
deforestation
massively impacts on not just because
you've taken down the trees which are
turning carbon dioxide into oxygen but
all of the other things that are
connected to that right
and and so there's focusing on one thing
and saying that's the thing we have to
deal with now
and the externalities that we
create in the meantime while doing so
i'm sorry but i've got a really really
big issue with that
yeah no i i would i would definitely
agree with you that we need to
be able to focus on externalities
because if you look at just efforts that
have been done in the past
uh say the the creation of biodiesel for
the european market
with jatropha farming and with uh
creating palm plantations in indonesia
um like the palm plantation creation
led to so much deforestation that you
actually
had a lower co2
sequestration in those forests uh
because
and great co2 emissions because they're
burning the forest to create these
palm plantations that people could drive
their cars with the biodiesel
in the european market so i mean i i
think we definitely
we definitely have to consider the these
economic drivers and what the impacts
will be
um i do want to match on to your point
about
uh soil and agriculture
because i think there if this is a
solution raising i think there's
actually a really interesting solution
uh framework around that
um like there's been a lot of
interesting stuff on biochar
um looking at how biochar could be used
for
sequestration and agricultural processes
and
help restore degraded soils
um so that might be an area that we
might want to
look into in terms of solutions
yeah especially if it's already
happening if it's not something that's
like off in the distant future i don't i
that's the first time i've encountered
that term so i don't know about it i'll
invite us to switch over
into the next section which is to
envision
our beautiful versions of the future
where
we we are working in alignment with the
world i can't imagine a different
beautiful future if you want to counter
jacob
dealing with climate change and the
environmental degradation sorry eric
well i was just saying that that doesn't
have to be an integrated we can just
concrete the whole thing over we don't
need plants and
and oceans and trees and and we
that just concrete the whole thing over
process the atmosphere artificially you
know what i mean we can make we can
maintain a perfectly livable environment
like that
there's eric's beautiful version of the
future
want to share your actual one
i will start um we live
within the within balance with nature
and we live abundant lives where
we have all of the delicious food we
need that
goes back to regenerating the soil we've
dealt with the entire
means of production so that it is cradle
to grave everything's be able to be
reproduced and reused we have access to
the science so that even
you don't have to have the debate
endlessly on whether climate change is
real and true we have access to it and
so we can leave it up to the scientists
who have our full backing to be like
yeah okay what do we need to do
in regards to all the that we're
pumping into the world
that if and when climate does change we
look at it as a global population and
say hey are some place is not livable
how do we move humans somewhere else or
how do we create within that do we live
in biodomes do we
do we um regenerate that part and and
figure out how to do it
and we work together science is open
sourced so that
um it's not proprietary behind closed
doors
we solved climate change so now we're
billionaires
it's you know every little incremental
change we're sharing and growing so that
we can we can learn
and adapt as we come and solution
raisings exist so that anytime there is
something that's that's crappy in the
world
you just need to get ten thousand people
together happy you know
have conversations in two to five give
out the idea the
solution we vote on the best one and we
make it and we keep improving it
we get there that's my beautiful future
anyone else
you go um there are sensors
everywhere uh
iot sensors that can measure
qualities about our world are
you know discreetly put everywhere that
needs to be measured
and they all talk to each other they're
all
powered by ai that can actually
communicate with each other
to build a more full picture
of what the world is like and
allow us to make decisions
based off of a
more complete understanding of the
situation that we're in
so allowing the
technology to take away
the the
a lot of the burden from us in terms of
sense making
and be able to put the pieces together
so that all we have to do is
i mean really have an incentive system
aligned with these
this iot network such that um
people get rewarded for doing the thing
that is
the right thing for the environment i
mean that that's the real ideal
situation is that
you'd have some type of system where
incentives can be aligned to
the world like literally what needs to
be done in the world versus what we
think needs to be done to the world
i think the more sensors that we have in
the world that can talk to each other
and are powered by ai that can
understand each other
uh the better it would be that's
my my vision
it's funny i guess mine is in some ways
the exact opposite of that
in that well i kind of feel that
this this notion that we have any
inkling of house of steward nature
is a a beautiful example of human
arrogance right and the the only thing
that knows how to steward nature is
nature and so
wherever possible leaving alone
just yeah
let the world rewild itself just leave
that
alone let it sort itself out
and uh you know only tamper with the
bits that we absolutely need to tamper
with right and
and and leave large swathes as i say
something those little bubbles of human
of human occupation right and we
organize that according to whatever
needs that we have but then surrounded
by
wild that we just that we just
leave alone and we on and and
you know the notion of we come from the
earth
and and honoring that by leaving the
earth alone insofar as we can right
all this modern stuff that we need to do
we we do
in enclosed sort of
anyway i've made my point rewilding as
much as possible is kind of is kind of
what i would like
to see
yes my utopian vision is um
scarcity is a thing of the past
and i think that if
we solved for scarcity
either like real scarcity or what i
think
in the west living in
manufactured scarcity through rivalrous
behavior um i think if we solved for
scarcity
people would be able to
just navigate the world in a in a
more realistic way we're competing with
one another which means we're
hoarding and we're we're doing damage
um because we're not working together um
i think removing scarcity about in so
many ways
that would be um a world i'd want to
live in
i'd agree with that i mean i think that
if we could have
a world where there was more cooperation
and
more
unified purpose for trying to solve
scientific problems and
um sharing of data i
i think we'd be in a better place so my
my utopian vision would be circular
economies
that were completely open source that
people could
uh really modify
like just like every product that we
have right now
is designed closed sort
pretty much every product is designed
closed sourced
and not circular and i'd like to see the
opposite of that where like
every single thing that we design is
open source and designed to be circular
and reused and recycled
and um yeah and that we can move back
towards more vocal production
um and local uh
resource uh resource control i feel like
globalization has
done damage to a lot of
the economics of um
just people working together in local
regions
and i i feel like it would be great if
we could move back towards like
you know i want to get this widget i can
get this widget
made 10 miles away
and that widget will come to me the same
day
and like we don't have to ship the
widgets all the way around the world
and have all that impact um
and yeah uh and to the sensors and data
um all four sensors just let's make
cameras
yeah i'm not big on cameras everywhere
can i just pick up on and just add
something to what i was saying
mostly picking up on what you were just
saying peter um
this idea of localization i think is it
it's not just i mean it is that
it is also that right sourcing things
locally reducing blah blah blah
but also it affords the opportunity
for small scale experimentation friendly
competition
maybe the gamification of this stuff
right where you can have
these local nodes in you know entering
into friendly
what's what's the best solution we can
come up with we've all got similar
situations all right well
let's let's let's start a little game
let's start a competition between us
to come up with a solution to this
particular problem we'll work on it
independently and then in whatever three
months time we'll get together so
you know you have uh because there there
is there is a there is a certain free
song created by competition right which
which spurs you on and so if you can
incorporate that
somehow into a context of broader
collaboration right we're competing
against each
other but in the common pursuit of
something that's going to
benefit all of us right i i really like
this notion of gamification on small
scales to actually
create large-scale solutions that emerge
to things
and with that we can switch over into
the next part which is the beautiful
um what jason possible what could we do
now with ten thousand people and a
hundred thousand dollars
because this is gamifying it right like
this is
there's dozens of people having these
and like who comes up with the best
solution to save the
world how horrible if someone else does
right like
it's fun to be part of it and but
hopefully and fun to
envision a better world and what could
we actually do if we had ten thousand
people
and a hundred thousand dollars possibly
to gamify
saving the world creating a better
sustainable
environment
well i came here uh with an idea already
that's pretty short i just the only
thing i could think of
was to pick an existing product
and try to make it better by reducing
the waste
somehow it's not a it's not a new idea
um so i i switched over to a laundry
detergent that uses less plastic because
you know it's like little it still uses
some but it's like little tide pod
things but you don't have the big
plastic container
because all those are shipped in a
cardboard box so i would just like
target one product
and say how can we make this more
environmentally friendly
i feel like that's within the scope of
the solution raising
i think yeah if we if there's one
that most people use
that is also something that the ten
thousand people could get together and
say right let's say detergent
hey what do you look for in a detergent
right maybe we have two or three
detergents one cent free
one hypoallergenic one regular or we
start with one
and figure out how do we produce that
for those 10 000 people and then if it's
done in a sustainable way where it's you
know carbon neutral or whatever we care
about
um and then ask you right like you can
already see the transparency of creating
that product
that the ten thousand people got
together to do that so you're gonna be
more open
like you're not gonna stop at the ten
thousand right it's like that's where it
starts to say hey what would get you to
use this detergent
i like this concept of gamifying things
uh those brought up
um i mean i just think about
how many people play like animal
crossing
or like any of these games where like
they're they're entering into this
uh digital world and
uh just doing meaningless things in the
digital world
um i'm wondering if there's a way that
we could gamify
people actually doing some
actual physical thing in the real world
uh that would have an impact like
planting trees or i don't know i mean i
don't know what the
actual solution would be but figure out
or the range of solutions could be
um but like figure out ways of
incentivizing people to
get out there and do physical
actions in the real world that manifests
uh more towards this direction
but encapsulating that somehow in a game
has anyone ever seen
read the book freedom tm
uh by daniel suarez it's a
it has a augmented reality game
that guides people into like rebuilding
the world in economic collapse i think
it's
it's actually a very apropos
book right now
i like the idea it's like a pokemon go
type where like you're
connecting with your neighbors and like
you know i picked up this piece of trash
i don't know something that is like fun
connection and also i'm a little
i mean my current special interest is
mlms don't get into it there's something
very different about
like leveling up together versus like
being in it on your own and then like no
no anyone can get to the part at the top
no you're there because the bottom
exists
but doing it in a way that it's like how
does vancouver compete with toronto or
how does like
have it be instead of like hockey which
i just don't care about
how can we but like and not our
governments either like us how can we
compete so that we can say hey we're the
more environmentally friendly
we have we reduced our carbon and making
it be sexy right making it be like this
is
because it doesn't need to be everyone
if there's 100 people in each city doing
it'd be fun
100 different people in a hundred
different cities well that's that's like
usually right it's
it scales up so you could do it in a
neighborhood i mean this is something
you could even do
with the ten thousand people hundred
thousand dollars the hundred thousand
dollars could form a prize pool right
and so every year every one of the ten
thousand people pays ten dollars into
an annual price of 100 which is
distributed a month and so
like rubbish you just picked up on trash
i mean that's a really good one to start
with
trash pickups right it can be it can be
done on a neighborhood level it can be
done on a city level as well right who
can have the cleanest
city streets right so this can be a
competition between cities and the
you know the winning city gets whatever
ten thousand dollars or something out of
the prize pool and the winning
neighborhood gets a hundred dollars out
of the prize pool
and this kind of thing and so you it
could i i
certainly as it attracts more than the
ten thousand this is something that
could
that could yeah and i mean picking up
trash is just one thing right water
quality i mean this is something that is
measurable right you can send people out
to test the water that comes out the
taps in people's homes
in various different neighborhoods
cities regions countries right and they
can all be
competing against each other for whose
citizens are drinking the cleanest water
right what a great competition to be
involved in
uh that's cool i i'm i like the idea for
the incentives
i mean and
talking about i don't eat out very much
because i walk to my grocery store and i
cook all my food
because that's you know i'm using less
fuel
i'm creating less pollution it's not
very cool
i'll tell you what like it doesn't seem
cool to in my world um
to other people or i leave all my lights
off most of the time
in my house because it saves energy and
that's
also not very cool but if i had a way to
yeah like get points on a scoreboard or
something and i'm competing
for less impact
kilowatt hours per person in households
or something like that there we go
there's another competition
absolutely this is all easily done right
easily sorted out easily done
it's a great idea i think it'd be cool
if we could mix
the the different areas of impact i mean
we've mentioned water electricity waste
management
like if if there's a scoring system that
could say
okay maybe i've like left my lights on
in my house but i've got a warm
composter
so like i can compare those different
behaviors
yeah so the warm composter gets you what
plus a hundred points a month and
leaving your lights on gets you minus a
point a day or something like that yeah
exactly sense of what the relative
impacts of these things are
yeah yeah yeah yeah absolutely it can
have that built into it also that's a
really good idea
that's a really good idea it almost
becomes like a currency then right it's
a way of valuing it it almost becomes a
a
a measurement of value yeah it's very
cool that's very cool i like that and if
we're doing it together
then we can also see where the
incentives we got the incentives wrong
right like i'm part of the co-housing
group and they have this recycling room
that they all they all use
and they're like they have this
competition of like
not a competition competition we're just
like can we use less waste right we
don't have enough room
and i'm like but wait like if you're not
bringing in less you're just gonna be
throwing out stuff if you're trying to
bring down your recycling right so that
you're using less it's like that's the
wrong incentive
it's like there has to be something
bigger but you could see that because
it's a small community
right so so it's more obvious and so to
say oh like we're picking up trash right
vancouver's picking up trash and
toronto's picking up trash
oh wait vancouver's throwing more trash
on the ground so that we can pick up
more trash
right so like let's let's figure out how
to how to re-organize
the um the incentives so that we're
actually having the impact that we want
to have
can i can i throw one other idea this is
not my idea this is the
jubilee you know you know where this
ideas come from um but
i i think that it's well worth
mentioning here and maybe it'll plant a
seed in someone that goes somewhere
right
um but kylie who we have a regular call
with on wednesday has this notion of the
global commons trust and this fits into
this potentially really well right
and that i don't fully understand it but
basically the idea is that there you
know that
there is commons out there right there's
all kinds of commons not just the
environment the air the water but
you know trust and uh you know there's
all kinds of commons out there and when
damage is done to the commons
compensation for that damage should be
should be um made payable right and and
so this this fits the the idea of
this as a currency with which the
commons can be valued right because
that's what we're talking about we're
talking about cleaning up things that
we're talking about cleaning up things
which are rightly
part of the commons um so it's a way of
valuing and incentivizing and ordering
that potentially as well i i
this is actually i'm we're gonna have to
tell kylie about this conversation later
jubilee i think this
this lines up really well with some of
my
um kind of thoughts about
changing the game that we play um
right now we play the game of capitalism
where we earn
as much money as we possibly can who can
earn the most and a lot of people have
won that there are winners of capitalism
so
how do you get the winners of capitalism
to play a different
game that can help the world
and my just immediate thought on that
was
in a gamification side of things for
every one dollar you get
one karma point right and that karma
point is measured on a digital system
that
people are playing it has to be adopted
by people right obviously but that
this is a point that you you have on
your profile in the same way you'd have
like an rpg or something of that nature
you can have different
types of karma points right i just came
up with the name karma points like it
could be anything
bitcoin for this no because bitcoin can
be traded this would be something for
hollow chain i think which holochain if
you guys haven't
looked into holochain it's really
awesome uh but holochain
is it it can measure like let's say for
example i put
a million dollars towards something that
is helping the commons right like i
don't need that million dollars anymore
the commons
has that like boom it's traded away but
like i should have
there should be a status that showed
that i did that because
then it's like oh look at me i still
have my
competition status going on like i've
done blah blah blah you can keep this
whole
rivalrous dynamic going on yet
it doesn't really it can be digital it
doesn't need to be
in real life if that makes sense so um
we can be competing to better the
commons
i like that for one instead of your like
net worth right you can start bragging
about right or whatever that is
but also when people who are
billionaires like bill gates
and and elon musk and stuff like they
have their vision
their utopian vision of what they're
trying to create in the world and a big
problem
is wait you've got that money us
all over that's a problem
and then you think you can envision a
better world but there's something kind
of cool about them just kind of
giving it back to the commons to decide
what that is so that we get to decide
and so the people who are already kind
of losing a game a
can be part of the people that decide
what is actually going to be done with
that money
and not done with like oh i give a
million dollars to cancer research
right and they they threw a gala and
they you know like
made a pharmaceutical thing that they
made money off of that's not actually
giving it to the commons we didn't
actually cure cancer with that
like having it be transparent anyway
yeah
i love that and there's there's ways to
make
to make it so that and i've been
thinking about this a little bit but
there's a way to do like a one-to-one
kind of um uh matching
from a a point that's on your system
that's in your
in your digital record
right but also getting up
a dollar in whatever this currency is as
well so like this could be a currency
specifically for
altruistic things or like helping the
commons so it could be you you kind of
multiply your worth
like for every one dollar you put in you
get one status point and one
currency digital currency that you can
actually do something with
in a that could help the world
um that that kind of
shift in thinking i think we if we lean
into
the fact that the digital world is
limitless
we can trick people into like
basically just like oh yeah like i want
this now i want
this status in this digital world and to
get that i have to
give all this money or do all these
things in order to help the real world
like sure okay but as long as i get my
like so and so
right like you can there's layers of
motivation you can have that
initial hedonistic motivation of like i
just want to have status
that eventually if you're constantly
looking for
good things to do in the world that
might
change and even if it doesn't change
like what's the difference
if you have somebody that's doing good
versus someone who is motivated to do
good because of what like what about who
cares about their motivations if they're
if everyone is doing that like
you know i i don't know i think it's
awesome
until you make it basically until you
make it yeah and even if you don't make
it
you can just keep faking it yeah and
who's going to judge you for that
like come on it makes it easier to be a
good person than it is to be a bad
person
like that that's the kind of system yeah
absolutely absolutely this
would this work so let's say
i saved up let's say i need
new shoes and i saved up enough money
and i could buy brand new nikes
um because that would be cool uh
and that would make me look like
hey he's got money he's um
you know got it going on um i want to
hang out
i'm just trying to be realistic here uh
but instead i go to the thrift store and
i buy some used
shoes because they'll probably work just
as good
for a while so can i get
points for buying at the thrift store
you could you know take this analogy out
of vehicles as well
to buy a new car that's shiny and gets
me lots of attention
um or i could buy a car that's 10 years
old
because that's probably you know better
um
how does this transfer into that kind of
thinking
to rip off that everywhere right yeah
it's everywhere but but to riff off that
it would have to be well a decentralized
so it's not one
person or company controlling all this
but the
the idea would be like you could either
get something
outside of the system or something
inside of the system
and whatever is inside of the system is
good for the world
and whatever is outside of the system is
whatever right so
you you get points for doing something
that is good for the world so
if i get a some nikes but these nikes
are
not in the system they don't have any
kind of
they haven't been accepted into because
they are
doing some shitty stuff to the world
right then
i'm probably not you know i could buy
those or i could get
a pair of shoes that are verified in the
system
for like though that company has offset
their carbon costs
and they have recorded that on a um
a system that tracks that i don't
know but like
if i get those shoes then i get x amount
of points versus if i get
the shitty nikes i don't get any points
right like
that that kind of dynamic is what i was
thinking about
like ecological ethics incentives
well i i don't see why it can't be both
i mean i don't see why it can't also be
what daniel was saying right
that you you make a choice to buy
something used rather than something new
and i don't why can't you get a karma
point for that right you know
growing your own tomatoes instead of
buying tomatoes in the supermarket
surely that's worth a karma point you
know or whatever but i i see no reason
why behaviors
can't also be rewarded i don't see why
it needs to be consumer choices
behaviors also then
certainly the there is the potential to
to accommodate that i mean
exactly how it works i don't know i mean
it's complex right but but
i see no reason why behaviors can't also
be incentivized in that
in that sort of way so i think that um
one thing to consider is
where where these karma points will
aggregate
um and this is something uh
that reminds me a lot of berkshire bucks
which was
a actual second currency in the u.s
that got approved in western
massachusetts
um as a local currency is reagan's
treasury secretary who did it
um and basically they created the second
currency for like local shopping
it was a big trial um everybody
went and shopped locally except they had
this huge problem where
after doing it for a year the
supermarket
had like a huge amount berkshire bucks
that they could not spend with their
just like distributors
across the nation because they didn't
want to accept
berkshire bucks like so so trying to
figure out like
what what will happen with the flow
of secondary currencies
i mean bitcoin's an interesting example
because
it actually managed to gain traction
globally
um it went from nothing to significant
value
in a comparatively short period of time
i mean
a decade um so
yeah it it it's interesting to think
about
kind of uh
how you deal with monetary flows and
whether uh other incentive systems will
act like monetary flows
so
is with currency maybe it's just you
know points karma points or whatever
it's not something you can explain
later but you can be like wow look at my
progress it's building up
and you could compare it with your
friends or something like that and
you know right now the only thing with
my friends
is hey i just bought a brand new uh you
know
car and how cool was that
i mention also um daniel's brought up a
few times that like
feeling of not being cool because of
working in this space right and feeling
like the rest like
there's so much that needs to change in
the world and people want the change but
they also don't want to be judged for
that change right like the amount of
people who care about fashion and makeup
and they want to be able to to like well
i don't want a new dress every every
every time i go to a new event but i
have to buy a new dress because
otherwise people are going to judge me
creating a space a culture of like
inclusivity where it doesn't matter what
the outside world thinks
because we accept you for that right and
like we know it's cool
to buy the secondhand shoes instead of
the nike shoes
and even if you don't mean your small
town or your big city you can't see it
but there's some amount of online space
and you know the people local to connect
with
although that maybe isn't the solution
for climate change it is right because
if you can't
if you don't feel like you can make
those changes
because of the judgment of the outside
world everyone feels that way
right and so giving people a space it to
be just like pokemon go
solution i'm sorry um climate change
game incentivized
hey right like this is this is fun
getting like leonardo dicaprio on it
getting people on it they kind of do
make it cooler
and also creating it in a way where it's
like who cares if they're involved or
not
we think it's cool and we like it
there's ten thousand of us right and
we're gonna sell we're gonna sell it
we're going to tell people about it
we're going to word them out get other
people involved because we're having fun
and doing it and that's what anything we
create hopefully is that it's a natural
attractor
and to to add to that this
i'm not going to go too deep into it
because it would be a little bit too
much to explain right now but
another incentive that you could add to
this
is that this each of these points these
karma points whatever you want to
say are they can also add to
your ai currency if you will so what if
everyone had an
ai concierge that could do
anything that you wanted and they were
paid in this currency
so in order to get your ai concierge
to line up your life the way you want it
to be to to
to do to make life super easy all you
have to do is
x right what is that x and like how can
we
kind of create a system like that
because that
that would be nice if you just had a
concierge 24 7 that would do whatever
you wanted to and all you had to do was
pay it in
a uh
that's it that's all you got to do it's
just giving people access
yeah finally the person he already
mentioned had said this beautiful thing
about biology how like biology isn't
in cells being like oh we're you're not
doing your job so we're not going to
give you any food right like it first
has to give you food and then you can
there's something about like having a
disability i'm like i need that
concierge before i can reduce my carbon
right like i started
using a french press i don't think
anyone should use a french press
everyday so now i'm using those horrible
peering pods things and it's like but
if if you don't mean there was there was
some kind of ai that could help me eat
better so that i could
i would that would be what i would i
would sign up and be like the first
thing i'm getting rid of is curing pods
right so it's like in order you give me
the ai and then i get i give that up
right and then for the next thing maybe
i have to prove that i did it or
something but there's also
yeah it could be like um it could be
kind of like a you know you have like a
credit system or something where
everyone
just by being a person has a certain
amount of credit that
by using the system and doing what the
system says which was
it inherently will make the world better
somehow you know with x then if you're
an active member of the system you pay
off that
that ai debt and then incur
more than get more ai wealth to do more
things with this ai so
i mean imagine going to a starbucks
picking up a tablet and just boop
it scans your face it knows who you are
and then it says oh hey here's all your
stuff here right
you just put it down grab like glasses
or something and like it knows who you
are
this whole system knows everything about
you and it says like oh
down the block there's somebody else
that needs a new pair
you can get point five service karma if
you just give them
one of these things oh cool sure no
problem and then pick up some trash on
the way there and you can get extra
points great no problem
right like having a system that makes it
really easy
to be a good person like that
that's something that i'm really like
wishing
the world to like wishing to exist in
the world and that's something i've been
kind of
thinking about a lot so i i want to
throw a little bit of a spanner into
these works i mean i
i too i've got quite excited about all
this but but something is starting to
dawn on me is that who gets to decide
what
is and is not a karma point-worthy act
right exactly this is a real this is a
potential real problem right
yeah and i just wanted to throw that in
there
and i working with ai i don't think it
should be ai
deciding what the incentive should be
whoever does get to decide they wield a
lot of power right the person who
describes that
they wield a lot of power over the
behavior of society so
it's a tricky one so i mean could be
like a wisdom of the crowds thing
where you like crowds force people
deciding what behaviors to incentivize
but then
i mean you get weird popular behavior
entertaining and all of that
yeah yeah so well you probably do it
more like the sam harris moral landscape
type of thing where your system
is not the same for all
groups but you have a system where you
kind of set the value
parameters for your group and you say
well i want to play inside this space
right but you would find the landscape
that works for you and so you've got
these different moral landscape
peaks you know hopefully you aren't
signing up for one that's really really
low um but
like a meta crowd source they'll all be
pretty good
um because you know human nature is
naturally pretty good
and we're shooting for something higher
but you wouldn't have a
value system that's ubiquitous for all
the people using the system
you'd have to have a way to have
different groups
i like that although i have to say if we
were starting with ten thousand hundred
thousand dollars we'd probably have one
and then wrench you know from there but
um we're getting close to the hour
so if we want to wrap up this part and
then we'll be switching over just to the
last bit which is sharing our
um most powerful one that we would like
to see that you'd want to be part of
so you can get that in the back of your
head we'll wrap up this part
anyone has any thoughts left on this
part before we can switch over that
yeah i think 10 000 10 000 people and
hundred thousand dollars is not enough
to
pull off a system like this that can be
adapted well but
maybe um it can be enough
to like
inspire a good faith
like game where people
self-report what they do like you can
say like hey guys we're doing this game
we make a mighty networks about it or
make some type of thing
and everybody
puts in what they've done
that is different from what they
normally do
and then like other people vote and they
say oh yeah i'll give you i'll give you
a point for that all right i'll give you
like
you know 10 points for that other people
can just
randomly arbitrarily assign points
to people and like make them feel good
that like
oh i'm i'm being recognized for doing
something that helps the world
like we can just kind of jerry-rig
something like that
in general um
it's uh i think it could i think it
could work
i guess i like what was said the most
about the cultural aspect
and saying well we need these spaces
where
uh people can be encouraged
for behaviors that we like and maybe
it's just my personal world that like i
don't
see a lot of that in my own world um
but it's definitely needed if this is
gonna work
i thought that was the switch over to
the other part does anyone else want to
share what they um
what their most powerful one is i don't
know if germans was that
just at this scale at the ten thousand
people hundred thousand dollar scale i
i think that the notion of maybe
starting to create some inter
neighborhood
competitions for rubbish collection
electricity consumption
um gardening production maybe
something like that you know um you know
food giving away to food banks whatever
i mean there's a million things if you
sat down and put a few heads to the job
there's a million things you could think
up you could you could think up to make
meaningful
fun competitions out of and then yeah
using the money as prize pools through
those competitions
i'm gonna just second eric um i think
that'd be
a great great way to
go in terms of setting some steps that
are doable
with limited resources and
achievable and could have big impact
i'm going to break my own i'm going to
break all the rules and say that because
i was using that hundred thousand
dollars in my head to create the
platform to be able to run the contest
so having a hundred groups of 100 all
over the world your 100 is more
localized and you're competing against
the other ones
and we use the hundred thousand dollars
to create the platform to make that work
and then we have some kind of outside
game a sponsor who puts in a million
dollars or puts in something that
actually maybe is a big prize
that it or we're just doing it because
it's fun right like you don't need to be
paid to go play hockey or go
do those things it's just like pay for
bragging rights vancouver
down the road sure you do it for karma
points down the road but for right now i
think waving dollar bills under people's
noses is a pretty is a pretty good
immediate incentive
and i agree it's not one that we should
be looking to perpetuate for very long
but but however we'd already have 10 000
people right
right now to get the ball rolling i
think it's maybe maybe usable
like we'd be creating an assist a gaming
something that was with the 10 000
people so it'd be like
breaking off in a hundred groups of 100
and then saying like if this isn't
something you would participate in
unless there's a million dollar prize
then you wouldn't vote for that anyway
so you wouldn't be part of the ten
thousand
so it's not you're in the five of us
to build the platform you're the one
that's taking the hundred thousand
dollars away to build the platform i'm
talking about using that
as price money yeah no it should be cool
because a hundred thousand would be a
thousand right so each person gets a
thousand and that's enough of an
incentive for most people
to be like yeah i'm gonna win that one i
mean are there any platforms that you
could
already use that that comes to mind like
if you want to use the money as prize
money
are there any platforms that are good
enough to like what was said like to
sort of jerry-rig an existing platform
maybe instead of karma points you use
likes or something or is
we could build something for 50 000 or
10 000
right like something and then have the
recipe price funny
there is always little plans to be
explored right
i love what we shared and then made it
better after like it was
powerful then here we go all right i
just want to give a little bit of a
closing for the
solution raisings um i want more people
to do this i want more people to show up
um and then hold their own and so i
don't know if i'm not ending them in
that way of like
you're invited to use this everywhere
and anywhere pick a topic you want show
up to this one
this is a way that we can have amazing
conversations
and create things in the world because i
don't know about everyone else but i
really enjoy this conversation
all right thank you everyone i'm just
gonna stop the recording